in this video we're going to talk about
how to add vectors
so a vector is a quantity that has
magnitude and direction
so let's say if we have a force vector
that's
100 newtons directed towards the east
the magnitude is the size of the force
it's 100 newtons
and the direction is east and let's say
if we want to add it to another force
that's directed east as well let's say
it's 50 newtons
the resultant sum of these two forces
is going to give us a net force of 150.
whenever you have two vectors that are
parallel to each other
you can simply add the numbers to get
the resultant sum
now let's say if we have
a 200 newton vector directed east
and 120 newton vector directed west
what is the resultant vector and also
specified the direction
so this is positive 200 because it's
directed towards the right this is
negative 120 because it's directed
towards the left
if you add these two
you should get a net force of positive
80.
now it's going to be smaller than the
original one but it's still directed
east
because this vector
is greater than this one
now as another example let's say if we
have a force vector that's 60 newtons
directed east
and another one that's 90 newtons
directed west
what is the resultant force vector
and what's the direction
so this is positive 60 that's negative
so we're gonna have
a net force of negative 30 newtons or
you could just say
30 newtons
directed west
now what if we have a force that's 80
newtons
directed north and another one
that's 120
direct itself
so 120 minus 8 is 40. so the net force
is going to be 40
itself
and if you recall
this is north
south east
west
now sometimes you may need to add two
vectors
that are not parallel or anti-parallel
to each other
so let's say if we have a third newton
force vector directed east
and a 40 newton force vector directed
north
what is the resultant force vector
if you have two vectors that are
perpendicular to each other
you could find the resultant force
vector
by finding the left of the hypotenuse of
the right triangle that is formed
so therefore
the resulting force vector is going to
be the square root of f1 squared plus f2
squared
let's call this f1
and this force f2
so it's going to be the square root of
30 squared
plus 40 squared
if you're familiar with the 345 triangle
then this is going to be the 30 40 50
triangle so the resultant force is going
to be 50 newtons
now sometimes in addition to finding the
magnitude of the resultant force vector
which is 50
you may need to find the direction as
well
so you got to find the angle theta
to find it you can use this formula it's
the
inverse tangent
of the
y component divided by the x component
so the force in the y direction is 40
and the x direction is 30.
so to find the angle it's going to be
our tangent
the opposite side which is the y value
of 40
over the adjacent side which is
the x value of 30.
hopefully you're familiar with sohcahtoa
sine is opposite over hypotenuse cosine
is adjacent over hypotenuse and tangent
is
opposite relative to theta over at the
adjacent side
the arc tangent of 40 over 30
is 53.1 degrees
so we can say that the resultant force
vector has a magnitude of 50 newtons and
a direction of 53.1 degrees relative to
the x-axis
let's try another example so let's say
if we have a force vector that's
50 newtons directed
west
and another one that's
120 newtons
directed
south calculate the magnitude of the
resulting force factor and find the
direction
so let's draw a triangle
so this side is 50
and this side is going to be 120
so the resultant force vector is the
hypotenuse of this triangle
so notice that it's in quadrant three
now if you're familiar with the 5 12 13
triangle
then the hypotenuse has to be 130.
so the resultant force vector is going
to be the square root of 50 squared
plus 120 squared
and that's going to turn out to be 130
newtons
so that's the magnitude of the resultant
force vector
now all we need to do
is find the angle
so first let's find a reference angle
to find a reference angle
use the arctangent formula
take the force in the y direction
divided by that in the x direction
but make it positive initially
this will give you an acute angle
between 0 and 90 and then you could
adjust it later
so our tan 120 over 50
will give you a reference angle
of 67.4
so here's the reference angle it's
inside the triangle
now what we need
is
the angle relative
to the positive x-axis
so if this is 180
then the resultant vector is 180
plus
67.4
relative to the x-axis
so it's at an angle of 247.4
so therefore
this is the resultant force vector
which has a magnitude of 130 but an
angle
of
247.4 degrees
so that's the answer
now let's say if we have a force vector
of
45 newtons directed east
and we wish to add it to a force vector
of 60 newtons directed south
find the magnitude of the resulting
force vector
and also the angle
so let's draw a triangle
so this is 45 and this is 60.
so let's find the magnitude of the
resultant force vector so it's going to
be the square root of 45 squared
plus 60 squared
which is 75 newtons
so that's the magnitude now we got to
find the angle
but let's find a reference angle first
so it's going to be arc tangent
the force in the y direction divided by
the force in the x direction so that's
over 45
which is 53.1
now that's the reference angle
the first force vector is positive
it's directed east
the second one is directed south
so therefore
the resultant force vector is in
quadrant four
now if this angle is 53.1
to find the angle
relative to the positive x-axis it's
going to be
360 minus 53.1 keep in mind a full
circle is 360 but you need to go back
53.1 degrees
so 360 minus 53.1
will give us an angle of 306.9
so the resultant force vector has a
magnitude
of 75 newtons
and it's directed at an angle of
306.9 degrees
relative to the positive x-axis
so this is the answer
so if you know the resultant force
vector
is going to be in quadrant one
then the angle is going to be the same
as the reference angle
and keep in mind the reference angle can
be calculated by taking the inverse
tangent of the force in the y direction
divided by the force in the x direction
and if you always make these positive
you're always going to get an acute
angle between 0 and 90 which is the
reference angle
now if you know the resultant force
vector is in quadrant two
then to find that angle it's going to be
180 minus the reference angle
if it's in quadrant three we cover this
one already it's 180 plus the reference
angle
and if you get an answer that's in
quadrant four it's going to be 360
minus the reference angle which was the
case in the last example
so
it's helpful to know these things or you
could just
see what to do visually once you graph
everything
now sometimes you may need to add
vectors
that are not parallel or perpendicular
to each other
so let's say if we want to add this
vector which is a 100 inch directed east
plus
another vector
let's say it has a magnitude of 150
but it's directed at 30 degrees
above
the x-axis
how can we find the resultant vector
first
let's re-list what we have
the first vector has a force of a
hundred
newtons
and its angle
it's east so it's on the x-axis so it
has an angle of zero degrees
the second force vector has a magnitude
of 150 newtons
and it has an angle of 30 degrees
relative to the x-axis
now
what you want to do is you want to add
these vectors using the component method
so you want to break these forces into
the components
add their respective x and y components
and then you could find the results in
force vector
so let's say if this is a force vector
this is the x component and this is the
y component
and here is the angle
f of x is equal to f
cosine theta
and f of y is f sine theta
f you can find it by using pythagorean
theorem it's f of x squared
plus
f of y squared
and the angle theta is the arc tangent
of f of y divided by f of x
so those are some formulas that you're
going to find useful
in this portion of the video
so what we need to do is find f one x
and f one y
so f one x is gonna be a hundred
cosine of zero
cosine of zero is one so a hundred times
one is simply a hundred
f one y is going to be a hundred sine of
zero sine of zero is zero a hundred
times zero
is going to be zero
now let's do the same for f2x
and f2y
f2x is 150
times cosine of 30 degrees
now if you type that in your calculator
make sure it's in
degree mode
so this will give you as a decimal
129.9 newtons
f2y that's going to be 150 times sine 30
which is just 75.
now what we need to do
is add up the x components
so if we add those two
values the sum
of the forces in the x direction is
going to be a hundred
plus
129.9
so that's going to be 229.9
and then we need to find the sum of the
forces in the y direction
which is just 0
plus 75 so that's simply
75.
so f of x
is
229.9 units and f of y
is simply
75 newtons
now let's go ahead and draw these values
on an xy plane
so f of x is 229
and f of y is 75.
the resultant force vector is the
hypotenuse
and to find it
it's going to be the square root of
f of x squared
plus f of y squared
so you should get
241.8
so that's the resulting force vector
that's the magnitude of it
now that we have the magnitude
we need to find the angle
so it's going to be
arc tangent
f of x i mean f of y which is 75
divided by f of x which is 229.9
so the angle which is already in
quadrant one
is 18.1 degrees
so now we have the magnitude and the
direction of the resultant force vector